Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology collection (SFU Archives collector)
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology collection (SFU Archives collector)
1967 - 2002
F-150
20 cm of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Archives and Records Management Department
The University Archives acquires, preserves and makes available three categories of materials: (1) the official records of the University, including those created by the Board of Governors, Senate, University committees, faculties, departments and administrative offices; (2) materials documenting the wider University community; and (3) historical research collections that promote the teaching and research activities of the University.
The Archives was established within the University Library in 1968 when librarian Liisa Fagerlund was appointed University Archivist on a half-time basis. She continued in this post until 1975 when she left the University. From 1975 to 1978, the Archives functioned within the Special Collections division of the Library. Archival duties were carried out by various library staff members. In 1978, the University Archives was established as a separate administrative unit outside of the Library. Donald Baird, recently retired as University Librarian, became University Archivist and held this position until his retirement in 1990. Jim Ross served as University Archivist from 1991 to 1993, and was succeeded by Ian Forsyth in 1994.
When the Archives was a function of the University Library, the University Archivist reported to the University Librarian. When the Archives was established as a separate administrative unit, the University Archivist reported directly to the University President. The reporting structure changed in 1986 when the University Archivist reported to the Vice-President, Research/Information Systems; in 1990, when the University Archivist reported to the Associate Vice-President, Academic; and in 1996, when the University Archivist reported to the Registrar/Dean of Students.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the collection is based on its subject matter.
The Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology (PSA) Department was established in 1965 as one of the original departments at SFU. It marked a significant academic innovation in that it united three separate disciplines under one head—the distinguished Marxist scholar Tom Bottomore. By the late 1960s, Bottomore had returned to England, and the department entered a period of scholarly and administrative turmoil. The crisis culminated in the Department being placed under trusteeship by the University administration and eight faculty members going on strike.
The collection consists of various files collected over the years by the staff of the University Archives to assist history students and other researchers. Includes press releases, reports, publications and other documents.
The materials were arranged by the Archivist.
Archives and Records Management Department; Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology
The material was collected by the SFU Archives.
All accessions have been processed as of February 2007. Further accruals may be added to this collection from time to time.
Please consult the inventories for the Swartz Collection, F 131; the Office of the Registrar, F-85, series 1; and the Department of Political Science, Sociology, and Anthropology, F-20.
For a view of the PSA crisis in a broader context, see the following book by Micheal Horn, Academic Freedom in Canada: A History, University of Toronto Press, 1999.
The files are open with no restrictions.
File lists are available.
- Press releases, 1969 - 1971; F-150-0-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
  published
  Textual records
  Open
- CAUT correspondence and reports, 1968 - 1971; F-150-0-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- Publications about PSA, 1970 - 1990; F-150-0-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- Norm Wickstrom (student paper), [ca 1970] - [ca 1979]; F-150-0-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- Letty Wilson memoir, 1993; F-150-0-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- Doug Cole letter, 1996; F-150-0-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- The Peak Newspaper articles, 1967 - 1971; F-150-0-0-0-7 (Newspaper box 150-2)
- Doug Cole - photocopies of letters, 1969; F-150-0-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- Roy Carlson interview, 1995; F-150-0-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- Academic Freedom in Canada by Michael Horn (excerpt), 1999; F-150-0-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- The PSA Department at SFU by Ronald McPhedran (student essay), 2002; F-150-0-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- Ann Messenger correspondence, 1969; F-150-0-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- C.A.U.T. Bulletin, vol. 16.2, December 1967; F-150-0-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- C.A.U.T. Bulletin, vol. 16.4, April 1968; F-150-0-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- C.A.U.T. Bulletin, vol. 17.1, October 1968; F-150-0-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- C.A.U.T. Bulletin, vol. 17.2, December 1968; F-150-0-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- C.A.U.T. Bulletin, vol. 18.2, 1970; F-150-0-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- C.A.U.T. Bulletin, vol. 19.1, 1970; F-150-0-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- C.A.U.T. Bulletin, vol. 19.2, 1971; F-150-0-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- C.A.U.T. Bulletin, vol. 20.1, 1971; F-150-0-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- C.A.U.T. Bulletin, vol. 20.2, 1972; F-150-0-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- C.A.U.T. Bulletin, vol. 20.3, 1972; F-150-0-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 150-1)
- C.A.U.T. Bulletin, vol. 23.3, December 1974; F-150-0-0-0-23 (Newspaper box 150-2)
- C.A.U.T. Bulletin, vol. 25.3, April 1977; F-150-0-0-0-24 (Newspaper box 150-2)
- C.A.U.T. Bulletin, vol. 25.4, September 1977; F-150-0-0-0-25 (Newspaper box 150-2)